<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction to Ethics on PHI 14</title>
    <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Introduction to Ethics on PHI 14</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 15:26:52 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Virtue 2</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-virtue-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 13:24:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-virtue-2/</guid>
      <description>What might be contemporary virtues? Your answers:
Sphere: illness Deficiency: resignation/avoidance/denial Excess: obsessive focus on illness Virtue: coping (positivity, realism, self-care, awareness) Sphere: work Deficiency: laziness Excess: work-obsessive Virtue: industrious/productive/motivated Sphere: making plans Deficiency: not following through Excess: rigidity Virtue: flexible dedication Sphere: thinking about ourselves Deficiency: insecurity Excess: vanity Virtue: confidence Sphere: decision-making Deficiency: indecision Excess: impulsiveness Virtue: reflective decisiveness Sphere: socializing Deficiency: meanness Excess: over-friendliness Virtue: friendliness Sphere: dealing with others&#39; agendas Deficiency: being a push-over Excess: stubbornness Virtue: assertiveness  Aristotle defines virtues (Nicomachean Ethics) Dispositions We are praised for virtues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Kantianism 2</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-kantianism-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 13:24:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-kantianism-2/</guid>
      <description>Utilitarianism vs. Kantianism Consider:
 Could we actually deploy these theories in our own thinking and acting? If we did deploy them, would we be behaving well — acting rightly and avoiding wrongs?  Responses   It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to apply either of the moral theories to situations from scratch.
 BUT: if we routinely apply the theories, they can come to be unconscious habits or have straightforward prescriptions - Kantianism generally yields classes of actions that are right or wrong: using people solely as means is wrong; lying is wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Kantianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-kantianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 15:33:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-kantianism/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s intrinsically valuable? Some things seem inappropriate to feel happy about.
 happiness about bad things [gruesome death? cruelty? cruel thoughts?] happiness out of step with reality  (BUT: says the Utilitarian, the happiness itself is still good even if we object to its source)
Kant: The one and only thing that&amp;rsquo;s intrinsically valuable is the good will.
Will: Capacity to push desires toward actions, or the capacity to choose and try to act on goals</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 8: Kantianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 22:19:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</guid>
      <description>German philosopher Immanuel Kant, working in the years before 1800, produced an audacious attempt to ground morality in the idea of the “good will.” We will look at how he does this in the book where he introduces his understanding of morality. Then we consider how we might apply Kantian thinking to particular cases. Finally, we identify criticisms of Kantian reasoning about morality and ways of addressing them.
Reading  “Reasons and Foundations,” chapter 16 of Blackburn, Being Good “The Categorial Imperative,” chapter 18 of Blackburn, Being Good Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals, by Immanuel Kant (1785), Early Modern Texts version.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test 1</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 09:14:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1/</guid>
      <description>This test is designed to take one hour. You may complete it during the class session, or you may submit it later in the day. Tests submitted any time on March 24 will be on time. Submit through the upload link at the course Blackboard site &amp;gt; Tests &amp;gt; Test 1.
Instructions Choose five (5) of the questions below under “Questions” to work on. For each of those five questions, write a one-paragraph answer, not shorter than five sentences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Utilitarianism 3</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-utilitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 15:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-utilitarianism/</guid>
      <description>The expediency objection Philippa Foot:
 A brilliant transplant surgeon has five patients, each in need of a different organ, each of whom will die without that organ. Unfortunately, there are no organs available to perform any of these five transplant operations. A healthy young traveler, just passing through the city the doctor works in, comes in for a routine checkup. In the course of doing the checkup, the doctor discovers that his organs are compatible with all five of his dying patients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Singer</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-singer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 14:49:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-singer/</guid>
      <description>If it&amp;rsquo;s in your power to save a life, you should, so long as you don&amp;rsquo;t have to sacrifice something worth as much.   even if there are others better positioned to help, who aren&amp;rsquo;t helping even if they&amp;rsquo;re from another country  Singer&amp;rsquo;s argument  If it&amp;rsquo;s in our power to prevent something bad from happening without sacrificing anything of comparable moral significance, we ought (morally) to do that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Utilitarianism 1</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-utilitarianism-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 16:11:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-utilitarianism-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on False Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-false-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 14:50:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-false-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Suppose a person “behaves as he does because of a system or socially institutionalized set of behaviors that are entrenched in the society, and that the function of the system” is sometimes opaque/not completely visible to the actor.
The actor in this situation exhibits false consciousness, because of the gap between what he thinks he&amp;rsquo;s doing (and why) and what he&amp;rsquo;s actually doing (and why).
 He thinks: he&amp;rsquo;s being kind / chivalrous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Naturalism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-naturalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 14:49:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-naturalism/</guid>
      <description>Evolutionary theory Evolution by natural selection: If organisms have heritable (= can be inherited, passed from parents to offspring) characteristics in which they vary from one another, and some of those variations contribute to their survival-to-reproduce and reproduction), then we will tend to see an increase in those beneficial characteristics over time. Most of the diversity of living things can be explained this way.
Ethics is a behavior. So, can we explain it by natural selection?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Egoism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-egoism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 14:59:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-egoism/</guid>
      <description>Psychological egoism = “the doctrine that the only thing anyone is capable of desiring or pursuing ultimately (as an end in itself) is his own self interest.” (Feinberg)
Why a threat to philosophical ethics?
Exclusively pursuing our self interest precludes pursuing others&#39; interests. And pursuing others&#39; interests (&amp;ldquo;altruism&amp;rdquo;) is one thing Ethics should prescribe.
Reason egoism might be true?
We can (cynically) analyze every possible case of potentially/nominally-altruistic behavior as really merely selfish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 15:00:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-relativism/</guid>
      <description>In what way are moral claims true/false? [for example, &amp;ldquo;Murder is wrong.&amp;quot;]
&amp;ldquo;Chocolate is delicious.&amp;rdquo; Is that true? Why or why not? &amp;ldquo;The Earth is round.&amp;rdquo; Is that true? Why or why not?
Ways of being true/false (or not)  Realism - Statements are true when they match reality (false when they don&amp;rsquo;t). Non-realism - Statements neither match nor fail to match reality; any opinion is as good as any other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Euthyphro</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-euthyphro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 14:49:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-euthyphro/</guid>
      <description>Euthyphro (Plato) Where: outside the courthouse
hoison = piety, holiness, righteousness, respectfulness toward gods, respectfulness
Socrates is facing trial for
 corrupting the youth rejecting the gods of Athens (lacking hoison) inventing false gods  Socrates defends his actions as displaying hoison
Euthyphro is at court pressing charges against his father
Socrates reacts with surprise at Euthyphro&amp;rsquo;s impiety towards his father — his lack of hoison
The Euthyphro dilemma  But if in fact what is dear to the gods and the holy were the same, my friend, then, if the holy were loved because it is holy, what is dear to the gods would be loved because it is dear to the gods; but if what is dear to the gods were dear to the gods because the gods love it, the holy would be holy because it is loved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 15:28:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-god/</guid>
      <description>Two threats from God First threat Fyodr Dostoevksy&amp;rsquo;s Brothers Karamazov, roughly: “If God is dead, everything is permitted” (= if there is no god, nothing is really unethical/wrong)
If God is a legislator of morality, then if there&amp;rsquo;s no God, there are or could be no rules of morality. Nothing is wrong.
Possible answers  God exists, and God legislates morality, and God backs up moral rules with reward/punishment. Though God doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, atheists nonetheless behave well because they find moral truths elsewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 15:50:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-justice/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 9: Virtue</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:19:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</guid>
      <description>How different does acting well look when we pull back our focus from individual actions, and whether they are right or wrong, to the structure of a whole human life? Acting well can become a matter of what best serves our living the best life we can. So, we have to ask, What&amp;rsquo;s the best life for a human being? What should we do to aim for that for ourselves?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 7: Utilitarianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:19:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</guid>
      <description>In this section, we encounter our first, comprehensive, positive theory of what&amp;rsquo;s right (and wrong) to do, and why. Utilitarianism, built from the idea that happiness is obviously valuable, resembles a variety of earlier philosophies that do the same, but developed its particular approach from the 18th Century forward. We begin with a slightly later Utilitarian philosopher, John Stuart Mill, who developed a sophisticated defense of it in the 19th Century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 6: False Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:18:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Could Ethics be a system of rules designed to keep free people down? Could it be just a bunch ideas many of us have come to believe in because we are weak, like Glaucon suggested?
Reading  “False Consciousness,” Chapter 7 of Blackburn&amp;rsquo;s Being Good  Learning questions  Try to develop your own example of false consciousness, if possible in an ordinary, familiar situation. That is, can you think of a situation in which someone actually does what they do for reasons that are different from the reasons they think are motivating them?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 5: Naturalism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:15:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</guid>
      <description>Does evolution favor selfish behavior as organisms pursue survival and reproduction in a competitive environment? Alternatively, what if we are ethical, but only because ethics is merely a behavior we&amp;rsquo;ve evolved to exhibit? Would that make it a sham? Can competing organisms rationally cooperate?
Reading  “Evolutionary Theory” by Simon Blackburn, in Being Good, pages 37–43. Listen to “Cooperation and Conflict,” by Philosophy Talk Starters via SoundCloud. (10 min, 35 seconds)1  Learning questions What are two ways natural selection might threaten ethics?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 4: Egoism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:15:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</guid>
      <description>Are we completely selfish? Can we do anything genuinely altruistic—for others&#39; benefit? If we are selfish, like Glaucon&amp;rsquo;s descriptive argument suggests, pursuing only our own pleasure, philosophical ethics looks like a sham. Is it?
Reading  “Egoism” by Simon Blackburn in Being Good (purchased book), pages 29–37. brief excerpts from “Psychological Egoism” by Joel Feinberg (1958), available on Blackboard &amp;gt; Course Documents.  Learning questions  What&amp;rsquo;s a reason to think that human beings are selfish?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 3: Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</guid>
      <description>Reading  “The Challenge of Cultural Relativism” by James Rachels. 1986. from The Elements of Moral Philosophy Temple University Press. Available through the course&amp;rsquo;s Blackboard site (under Course Documents). Note: this text, like some others we&amp;rsquo;ll read, includes some outdated language, like “Eskimo”—a word some of those it is used to refer to find unacceptable; I suggest not using it.  Learning questions  What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between general relativism and moral relativism?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 2: God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</guid>
      <description>What is ethics if there is no God, or, What would become of ethics if there were no God? If there is a God, does that make all further ethical discussion superfluous?
Reading  “The Death of God” from Being Good, by Simon Blackburn, pages 9–19. (This is the one book you need to purchase for this course.) Euthyphro (excerpt from Reginald Allen&amp;rsquo;s translation), by Plato. Available through Hofstra library here, login required.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 1: The Problem of Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 21:58:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</guid>
      <description>Are there any reasons not to behave unjustly, if we can get away with it? We observe Plato asking this question through a “thought experiment.”
Reading  Plato, “The Ring of Gyges,” an excerpt from his longer work Republic.  See also  “Plato” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Richard Kraut “Plato’s Ethics and Politics in The Republic” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Eric &amp;ldquo;Brown&amp;rdquo;  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test 1 Information</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 14:14:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1-info/</guid>
      <description>The first test, on Wednesday March 24, will be released at the beginning of the class session (11:20 AM) through a Blackboard announcement. The test is designed to take one hour. You may complete it during the class session, or you may submit it later in the day. Tests submitted any time on March 24 will be on time. Submit through the upload link at the course Blackboard site &amp;gt; Tests &amp;gt; Test 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assignment 1</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 12:17:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-1/</guid>
      <description>Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve spent time with each of the three major (most prominent, most discussed) theories of recent philosophical ethics, and have thought about how to apply them to situations, I want you to think about how you would apply them to real situations.
Find in you memory a real example of a choice that has moral dimensions, as experienced by you or someone you directly know. It could be a dilemma—a situation in which there are two or more seemingly-compelling options—but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Grades</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/interpreting-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 19:55:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/interpreting-grades/</guid>
      <description>This note about grading and interpreting grades just adds some detail to what the course syllabus already says about grading.
 4-point scale Writing assignment grades Test grades Overall course grades    4-point scale Grades in this course are assigned and calculated using Hofstra&amp;rsquo;s 4-point scale (described here in the Hofstra Bulletin). Following the Bulletin, the alphabetical grades, including plus (+) and minus (–), have the following 4-point scale values (and vice versa):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participation Rubric</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/participation-rubric/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 21:25:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/participation-rubric/</guid>
      <description>This is the participation rubric to be used for grading participation in this course. Read it as saying “A student who demonstrates … earns a grade of X,” where X is the letter grade at the top of the column.1
   A B C D F     Active role in discussions, drawing on texts Regular, constructive participation drawing on texts Inconsistent constructive participation based on texts Vague comments reflecting limited engagement with texts Persistent lack of engagement with texts   Full preparation for approximately every class Substantial preparation, normally Inconsistent evidence of preparation Rare evidence of participation No positive evidence of participation   Success at advancing level and depth of discussion, persistently Regular contributions based on assigned material, which sometimes improve discussion and never diminish it Rare or no significant contribution to the level of discussion while not reducing it Activity sometimes diminishing the discussion and the classroom environment Activity regularly diminishing the discussion and the classroom environment   Active engagement with and listening to peers, persistently Sincere efforts to interact with peers, normally Limited engagement with peers Rare interaction with peers No interaction with peers      This rubric is significantly based on, and lightly adapted from, one written by another philosophy professor, Jay Odenbaugh.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
