<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction to Ethics on PHI 14</title>
    <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Introduction to Ethics on PHI 14</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 10:53:46 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mid-semester Advisories</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/msa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 11:39:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/msa/</guid>
      <description>Mid-semester Advisories Hofstra faculty issue mid-semester advisories in the seventh week of the semester to let students know if they think there is a reason for concern, at that early stage, about their performance so far in the course. It is a preliminary flag, early in the semester, that there may be reason for concern at that point. As the Provost&amp;rsquo;s website instructs:
it is expected that students receive early advisory that reflects on their progress in their courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Grades</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/interpreting-grades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 11:41:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/interpreting-grades/</guid>
      <description>This note about grading and interpreting grades just adds some detail to what the course syllabus already says about grading.
4-point scale Grades in this course are assigned and calculated using Hofstra&amp;rsquo;s 4-point scale (described here in the Hofstra University Bulletin). Following the Bulletin, the alphabetical grades, including plus (+) and minus (–), have the following 4-point scale values (and vice versa):
letter 4pt Student’s academic performance … A 4.0 “was of honors level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participation Rubric</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/participation-rubric/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 11:41:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/participation-rubric/</guid>
      <description>This is the participation rubric to be used for grading participation in this course. Read it as saying “A student who demonstrates … earns a grade of X,” where X is the letter grade at the top of the column.1
A B C D F Active role in discussions, drawing on texts Regular, constructive participation drawing on texts Inconsistent constructive participation based on texts Vague comments reflecting limited engagement with texts Persistent lack of engagement with texts Full preparation for approximately every class Substantial preparation, normally Inconsistent evidence of preparation Rare evidence of participation No positive evidence of participation Success at advancing level and depth of discussion, persistently Regular contributions based on assigned material, which sometimes improve discussion and never diminish it Rare or no significant contribution to the level of discussion while not reducing it Activity sometimes diminishing the discussion and the classroom environment Activity regularly diminishing the discussion and the classroom environment Active engagement with and listening to peers, persistently Sincere efforts to interact with peers, normally Limited engagement with peers Rare interaction with peers No interaction with peers This rubric is significantly based on, and lightly adapted from, one written by philosophy professor Jay Odenbaugh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 11: Foundations</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 16:37:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/foundations/</guid>
      <description>We return to the question of the foundations of ethics — indeed to whether ethics has foundations. Blackburn writes “we had to acknowledge the threat of relativism, nihilism, and scepticism.… Are truth and knowledge possible, or does reasoning about what to do eventually hinge on nothing but brute will? Or are there yet other alternatives?” (Being Good, 108).
Reading “Contracts and Discourse,” chapter 19 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “The Common Point of View,” chapter 20 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “Confidence Restored,” chapter 21 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn (about 10 pages total)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 10: Cases</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 16:36:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/cases/</guid>
      <description>Having considered the major moral theories of recent philosophical ethics, we think through the moral dimensions of some cases. What do each of the theories have to say about them? Are the theories, as we&amp;rsquo;ve discussed them, adequate for analyzing these cases?
Reading/viewing For each of these films, consider making a few notes that prepare you to discuss them.
Watch: Moral Dilemmas … Can Ethics Help? (1998, Intelecom, 28 min.). Freely available on YouTube at the link.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 9: Virtue</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 16:36:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</guid>
      <description>How different does acting well look when we pull back our focus from individual actions, and whether they are right or wrong, to the structure of a whole human life? Acting well can become a matter of what best serves our living the best life we can. So, we have to ask, What&amp;rsquo;s the best life for a human being? What should we do to aim for that for ourselves?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 8: Kantianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 16:36:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</guid>
      <description>German philosopher Immanuel Kant, working in the years before 1800, produced an audacious attempt to ground morality in the idea of the “good will.” We will look at how he does this in the book where he introduces his understanding of morality. Then we consider how we might apply Kantian thinking to particular cases. Finally, we identify criticisms of Kantian reasoning about morality and ways of addressing them.
Reading “Reasons and Foundations,” chapter 16 of Blackburn, Being Good “The Categorial Imperative,” chapter 18 of Blackburn, Being Good Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals, by Immanuel Kant (1785), Early Modern Texts version.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test 2 Information</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-2-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 13:51:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-2-info/</guid>
      <description>General instructions The test will be designed take you not more than 90 minutes, but you will have two hours (120 minutes) to complete it. You will need to write answers in pen, on paper. Your answer should be in sentences rather than fragments or bullet points or similar (unless something else is specified by the question).
Format You will be asked to write answers to six of the questions presented by the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test 1 Information</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 13:53:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tests/test-1-info/</guid>
      <description>Instructions The test will be designed to take about an hour on average, and to take not more than 85 minutes (which is to say, class time).
Format The test will consist of six short (5–8 sentences), separate paragraphs you&amp;rsquo;ll need to write in response to questions that are reproduced in the list of “Possible test questions” below. That list is a test bank of possible questions, some of which are the actual questions that will be on the test, exactly as they will be written on the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assignment 1</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 08:53:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-1/</guid>
      <description>In our readings so far this semester, we have been observing authors making claims, considering possible objections to the support for those claims, and then replying to the objections, in order to solidify their original claims. We have observed repeatedly how good objections do not just deny others&amp;rsquo; claims or conclusions. Rather, they try to show that at least one reason offered in support of the conclusion might actually not be a good reason to accept it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 7: Utilitarianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:05:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</guid>
      <description>In this section, we encounter our first, comprehensive, positive theory of what&amp;rsquo;s right (and wrong) to do, and why. Utilitarianism, built from the idea that happiness is obviously valuable, resembles a variety of earlier philosophies that do the same, but developed its particular approach from the 18th Century forward. We begin with a slightly later Utilitarian philosopher, John Stuart Mill, who developed a sophisticated defense of it in the 19th Century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 6: False Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:04:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Could Ethics be a system of rules designed to keep free people down? Could it be just a bunch ideas many of us have come to believe in because we are weak, like Glaucon suggested?
Reading “False Consciousness,” Chapter 7 of Blackburn&amp;rsquo;s Being Good Learning questions Try to develop your own example of false consciousness, if possible in an ordinary, familiar situation. That is, can you think of a situation in which someone actually does what they do for reasons that are different from the reasons they think are motivating them?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 5: Naturalism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:04:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</guid>
      <description>Does evolution favor selfish behavior as organisms pursue survival and reproduction in a competitive environment? Alternatively, what if we are ethical, but only because ethics is merely a behavior we&amp;rsquo;ve evolved to exhibit? Would that make it a sham? Can competing organisms rationally cooperate?
Reading “Evolutionary Theory” by Simon Blackburn, in Being Good, pages 37–43. Listen to “Cooperation and Conflict,” by Philosophy Talk Starters via SoundCloud. (10 min, 35 seconds)1 The Descent of Man and Selection in Relation to Sex (1871), by Charles Darwin, excerpt we discussed in class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 4: Egoism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:04:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</guid>
      <description>Are we completely selfish? Can we do anything genuinely altruistic—for others&amp;rsquo; benefit? If we are selfish, like Glaucon&amp;rsquo;s descriptive argument suggests, pursuing only our own pleasure, philosophical ethics looks like a sham. Is it?
Reading “Egoism” by Simon Blackburn in Being Good (eBook through Axinn Library login, or search for “Being Good” directly in the Library Catalog “Discovery” search box), pages 29–37. brief excerpts from “Psychological Egoism” by Joel Feinberg (1958), available on Blackboard &amp;gt; Course Documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 3: Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:04:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</guid>
      <description>Moral Relativism is the view that while there are no objective ethical truths (like “murder is wrong”), there are ethical truths within cultures. We evaluate this suggestion, reflecting on arguments for and against it. (We&amp;rsquo;ll consider more arguments for and against it when we get to the virtue topic.)
Reading “The Challenge of Cultural Relativism” by James Rachels. 1986. from The Elements of Moral Philosophy Temple University Press. Available through the course&amp;rsquo;s Blackboard site (under Course Documents).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 2: God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:04:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</guid>
      <description>What is ethics if there is no God, or, What would become of ethics if there were no God? If there is a God, does that make all further ethical discussion superfluous?
Reading “The Death of God” from Being Good, by Simon Blackburn, pages 9–19. This book is available as an eBook for unlimited concurrent users through Hofstra Axinn Library. Access it here through the Library, or search for “Being Good” directly in the Library Catalog “Discovery” search box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 1: The Problem of Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 10:49:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</guid>
      <description>Are there any reasons not to behave unjustly, if we can get away with it? We examine how Plato asks this question through a “thought experiment.” Plato has his character Glaucon stake out a challenging position on this question.
Reading Plato, “The Ring of Gyges,” an excerpt from his longer work Republic. Reading questions The text takes the form of a conversation, though with extended speeches by each speaker. As the text opens (and for most of it, except briefly where Socrates interrupts, as highlighted by the sidenote) the speaker is Glaucon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assignment 2</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 12:37:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/assignments/assignment-2/</guid>
      <description>[ details to come ]</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
