<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Topics on PHI 14</title>
    <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Topics on PHI 14</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 16:06:26 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Topic 12: Foundations</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 16:06:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/foundations/</guid>
      <description>We return to the question of the foundations of ethics — indeed to whether ethics has foundations. Blackburn writes “we had to acknowledge the threat of relativism, nihilism, and scepticism.… Are truth and knowledge possible, or does reasoning about what to do eventually hinge on nothing but brute will? Or are there yet other alternatives?” (Being Good, 108).
Reading  “Contracts and Discourse,” chapter 19 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “The Common Point of View,” chapter 20 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “Confidence Restored,” chapter 21 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn  (about 10 pages total)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 11: Rights</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 16:06:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/rights/</guid>
      <description>In discussing the cases in the Cases section, we found that the language of “rights” offers another way of thinking about the moral dimensions of situations. Here we consider what rights are, whether anyone has any, why we have them (if we do), and what implications they might have for other moral ideas like duty and freedom.
Reading  “Freedom from the Bad,” chapter 13 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “Freedom and Paternalism,” chapter 14 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn “Rights and Natural Rights,” chapter 15 of Being Good, by Simon Blackburn  (about 14 pages total)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 10: Cases</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 13:40:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/cases/</guid>
      <description>Having considered the major moral theories of recent philosophical ethics, we think through the moral dimensions of some cases. What do each of the theories have to say about them? Are the theories, as we&amp;rsquo;ve discussed them, adequate for analyzing these cases?
Reading/viewing For each of these films, consider making a few notes that prepare you to discuss them.
  Watch: Moral Dilemmas … Can Ethics Help? (1998, Intelecom, 28 min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 9: Virtue</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 22:19:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/virtue/</guid>
      <description>How different does acting well look when we pull back our focus from individual actions, and whether they are right or wrong, to the structure of a whole human life? Acting well can become a matter of what best serves our living the best life we can. So, we have to ask, What&amp;rsquo;s the best life for a human being? What should we do to aim for that for ourselves?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 8: Kantianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 22:19:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/kantianism/</guid>
      <description>German philosopher Immanuel Kant, working in the years before 1800, produced an audacious attempt to ground morality in the idea of the “good will.” We will look at how he does this in the book where he introduces his understanding of morality. Then we consider how we might apply Kantian thinking to particular cases. Finally, we identify criticisms of Kantian reasoning about morality and ways of addressing them.
Reading  “Reasons and Foundations,” chapter 16 of Blackburn, Being Good “The Categorial Imperative,” chapter 18 of Blackburn, Being Good Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals, by Immanuel Kant (1785), Early Modern Texts version.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 7: Utilitarianism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:19:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/utilitarianism/</guid>
      <description>In this section, we encounter our first, comprehensive, positive theory of what&amp;rsquo;s right (and wrong) to do, and why. Utilitarianism, built from the idea that happiness is obviously valuable, resembles a variety of earlier philosophies that do the same, but developed its particular approach from the 18th Century forward. We begin with a slightly later Utilitarian philosopher, John Stuart Mill, who developed a sophisticated defense of it in the 19th Century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 6: False Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:18:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/false-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Could Ethics be a system of rules designed to keep free people down? Could it be just a bunch ideas many of us have come to believe in because we are weak, like Glaucon suggested?
Reading  “False Consciousness,” Chapter 7 of Blackburn&amp;rsquo;s Being Good  Learning questions  Try to develop your own example of false consciousness, if possible in an ordinary, familiar situation. That is, can you think of a situation in which someone actually does what they do for reasons that are different from the reasons they think are motivating them?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 5: Naturalism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:15:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/naturalism/</guid>
      <description>Does evolution favor selfish behavior as organisms pursue survival and reproduction in a competitive environment? Alternatively, what if we are ethical, but only because ethics is merely a behavior we&amp;rsquo;ve evolved to exhibit? Would that make it a sham? Can competing organisms rationally cooperate?
Reading  “Evolutionary Theory” by Simon Blackburn, in Being Good, pages 37–43. Listen to “Cooperation and Conflict,” by Philosophy Talk Starters via SoundCloud. (10 min, 35 seconds)1  Learning questions What are two ways natural selection might threaten ethics?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 4: Egoism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:15:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/egoism/</guid>
      <description>Are we completely selfish? Can we do anything genuinely altruistic—for others&#39; benefit? If we are selfish, like Glaucon&amp;rsquo;s descriptive argument suggests, pursuing only our own pleasure, philosophical ethics looks like a sham. Is it?
Reading  “Egoism” by Simon Blackburn in Being Good (purchased book), pages 29–37. brief excerpts from “Psychological Egoism” by Joel Feinberg (1958), available on Blackboard &amp;gt; Course Documents.  Learning questions  What&amp;rsquo;s a reason to think that human beings are selfish?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 3: Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</guid>
      <description>Moral Relativism is the view that while there are no objective ethical truths (like “murder is wrong”), there are ethical truths within cultures. We evaluate this suggestion, reflecting on arguments for and against it. (We&amp;rsquo;ll consider more arguments for and against it when we get to the virtue topic.)
Reading  “The Challenge of Cultural Relativism” by James Rachels. 1986. from The Elements of Moral Philosophy Temple University Press. Available through the course&amp;rsquo;s Blackboard site (under Course Documents).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 2: God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</guid>
      <description>What is ethics if there is no God, or, What would become of ethics if there were no God? If there is a God, does that make all further ethical discussion superfluous?
Reading  “The Death of God” from Being Good, by Simon Blackburn, pages 9–19. (This is the one book you need to purchase for this course.) Euthyphro (excerpt from Reginald Allen&amp;rsquo;s translation), by Plato. Available through Hofstra library here, login required.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 1: The Problem of Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 21:58:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</guid>
      <description>Are there any reasons not to behave unjustly, if we can get away with it? We observe Plato asking this question through a “thought experiment.”
Reading  Plato, “The Ring of Gyges,” an excerpt from his longer work Republic.  See also  “Plato” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Richard Kraut “Plato’s Ethics and Politics in The Republic” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Eric &amp;ldquo;Brown&amp;rdquo;  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
