<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>notes on PHI 14</title>
    <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tags/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in notes on PHI 14</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 15:04:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tags/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Utilitarianism 3</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-utilitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 15:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-utilitarianism/</guid>
      <description>The expediency objection Philippa Foot:
 A brilliant transplant surgeon has five patients, each in need of a different organ, each of whom will die without that organ. Unfortunately, there are no organs available to perform any of these five transplant operations. A healthy young traveler, just passing through the city the doctor works in, comes in for a routine checkup. In the course of doing the checkup, the doctor discovers that his organs are compatible with all five of his dying patients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Singer</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-singer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 14:49:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-singer/</guid>
      <description>If it&amp;rsquo;s in your power to save a life, you should, so long as you don&amp;rsquo;t have to sacrifice something worth as much.   even if there are others better positioned to help, who aren&amp;rsquo;t helping even if they&amp;rsquo;re from another country  Singer&amp;rsquo;s argument  If it&amp;rsquo;s in our power to prevent something bad from happening without sacrificing anything of comparable moral significance, we ought (morally) to do that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Utilitarianism 1</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-utilitarianism-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 16:11:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-utilitarianism-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on False Consciousness</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-false-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 14:50:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-false-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Suppose a person “behaves as he does because of a system or socially institutionalized set of behaviors that are entrenched in the society, and that the function of the system” is sometimes opaque/not completely visible to the actor.
The actor in this situation exhibits false consciousness, because of the gap between what he thinks he&amp;rsquo;s doing (and why) and what he&amp;rsquo;s actually doing (and why).
 He thinks: he&amp;rsquo;s being kind / chivalrous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Naturalism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-naturalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 14:49:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-naturalism/</guid>
      <description>Evolutionary theory Evolution by natural selection: If organisms have heritable (= can be inherited, passed from parents to offspring) characteristics in which they vary from one another, and some of those variations contribute to their survival-to-reproduce and reproduction), then we will tend to see an increase in those beneficial characteristics over time. Most of the diversity of living things can be explained this way.
Ethics is a behavior. So, can we explain it by natural selection?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Egoism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-egoism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 14:59:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-egoism/</guid>
      <description>Psychological egoism = “the doctrine that the only thing anyone is capable of desiring or pursuing ultimately (as an end in itself) is his own self interest.” (Feinberg)
Why a threat to philosophical ethics?
Exclusively pursuing our self interest precludes pursuing others&#39; interests. And pursuing others&#39; interests (&amp;ldquo;altruism&amp;rdquo;) is one thing Ethics should prescribe.
Reason egoism might be true?
We can (cynically) analyze every possible case of potentially/nominally-altruistic behavior as really merely selfish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 15:00:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-relativism/</guid>
      <description>In what way are moral claims true/false? [for example, &amp;ldquo;Murder is wrong.&amp;quot;]
&amp;ldquo;Chocolate is delicious.&amp;rdquo; Is that true? Why or why not? &amp;ldquo;The Earth is round.&amp;rdquo; Is that true? Why or why not?
Ways of being true/false (or not)  Realism - Statements are true when they match reality (false when they don&amp;rsquo;t). Non-realism - Statements neither match nor fail to match reality; any opinion is as good as any other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Euthyphro</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-euthyphro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 14:49:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-euthyphro/</guid>
      <description>Euthyphro (Plato) Where: outside the courthouse
hoison = piety, holiness, righteousness, respectfulness toward gods, respectfulness
Socrates is facing trial for
 corrupting the youth rejecting the gods of Athens (lacking hoison) inventing false gods  Socrates defends his actions as displaying hoison
Euthyphro is at court pressing charges against his father
Socrates reacts with surprise at Euthyphro&amp;rsquo;s impiety towards his father — his lack of hoison
The Euthyphro dilemma  But if in fact what is dear to the gods and the holy were the same, my friend, then, if the holy were loved because it is holy, what is dear to the gods would be loved because it is dear to the gods; but if what is dear to the gods were dear to the gods because the gods love it, the holy would be holy because it is loved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 15:28:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-god/</guid>
      <description>Two threats from God First threat Fyodr Dostoevksy&amp;rsquo;s Brothers Karamazov, roughly: “If God is dead, everything is permitted” (= if there is no god, nothing is really unethical/wrong)
If God is a legislator of morality, then if there&amp;rsquo;s no God, there are or could be no rules of morality. Nothing is wrong.
Possible answers  God exists, and God legislates morality, and God backs up moral rules with reward/punishment. Though God doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, atheists nonetheless behave well because they find moral truths elsewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 15:50:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/notes/notes-on-justice/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
