<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>topics on PHI 14</title>
    <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tags/topics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in topics on PHI 14</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:52 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/tags/topics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Topic 3: Relativism</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/relativism/</guid>
      <description>Reading  “The Challenge of Cultural Relativism” by James Rachels. 1986. from The Elements of Moral Philosophy Temple University Press. Available through the course&amp;rsquo;s Blackboard site (under Course Documents).  Learning questions  What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between general relativism and moral relativism? What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between moral relativism and moral anti-realism? What are Rachels&amp;rsquo;s two main arguments against (cultural) moral relativism? Does Rachels demonstrate that moral relativism is false? What exactly does he show?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 2: God</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 22:14:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/god/</guid>
      <description>What is ethics if there is no God, or, What would become of ethics if there were no God? If there is a God, does that make all further ethical discussion superfluous?
Reading  “The Death of God” from Being Good, by Simon Blackburn, pages 9–19. (This is the one book you need to purchase for this course.) Euthyphro (excerpt from Reginald Allen&amp;rsquo;s translation), by Plato. Available through Hofstra library here, login required.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 1: The Problem of Justice</title>
      <link>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 21:58:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chreliot.github.io/phi14/topics/the-problem-of-justice/</guid>
      <description>Are there any reasons not to behave unjustly, if we can get away with it? We observe Plato asking this question through a “thought experiment.”
Reading  Plato, “The Ring of Gyges,” an excerpt from his longer work Republic.  See also  “Plato” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Richard Kraut “Plato’s Ethics and Politics in The Republic” in the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, by Eric &amp;ldquo;Brown&amp;rdquo;  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
